<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A trew copie of the mutuall band betuix the castell and toun of Edinburgh contractit in the obedience of the kingis Maiestie our souerane lord, publischit that all men may the better persaue how the Laird of Grange, aganis his faith, honour and promeis, is and hes bene, the instrument and occasioun, of the present vnquyetnes and bypast vastatioun of the toun, to the suppressing of the exercise of Goddis trew religioun, the hinderance of iustice and policie, and calamitie of the haill commoun wealth.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1573</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12560</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856283</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856283</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12560)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1306:2b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A trew copie of the mutuall band betuix the castell and toun of Edinburgh contractit in the obedience of the kingis Maiestie our souerane lord, publischit that all men may the better persaue how the Laird of Grange, aganis his faith, honour and promeis, is and hes bene, the instrument and occasioun, of the present vnquyetnes and bypast vastatioun of the toun, to the suppressing of the exercise of Goddis trew religioun, the hinderance of iustice and policie, and calamitie of the haill commoun wealth.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Be Robert Lekpreuik,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprentit at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Do. M. D. LXXIII [1573]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Agreement to support James VI and regent James Stewart, Earl of Moray.</note>
                  <note>Identified as second part of STC 11184 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed with STC 21938.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in: Great Britain. Public Record Office.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="sco">sco</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moray, James Stewart, --  Earl of, ca. 1531-1570.</term>
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625.</term>
               <term>Edinburgh Castle (Edinburgh, Scotland). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  James 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="sco">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ a trew copie of the mutuall band betuix the caſtell and toun of Edinburgh, contracrit in the obedience of the Kingis Maieſtie our Souerane Lord, publiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hit that all men may the better perſaue how the Laird of Grange, agains his faith, honour and promeis, is and hes bene, the Inſtrument and occaſioun, of the preſent vnquyetnes and bypaſt vaſtatioun of the toun, to the ſuppreſſing of the exerciſe of Goddis trew Religioun, the hinderance of Iuſtice and Policie, and calamitie of the haill commoun wealth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T Edinburgh the viij. day of Maij, the ȝeir of God ane thouſand fyue hundreth, thre ſcoir and aucht ȝeiris. It is appointit, aggreit, and finally contractit and bound in vp, betuix the richt honorabill ſchir Williame Kirkcaldie of Grange Knicht Capitane of the caſtell of Edinburgh, for him ſelf, kin, freindis, ſeruandis, aſſiſtaris and partakaris on that ane part. And the richt honorabill Symon Preſtoun of Craigmillar of that Ilk Knicht, Proueſt of the Burgh of Edinburgh, for him ſelf, the Bailleis, counſal, Communitie and haill Inhabitantis of the ſaid Burgh on the vther part: in maner forme and effect as efter followis. That is to ſay, Forſamekle as it is not vnknawin to thame, how that the Quene our Soueranes deareſt Mother with certane of the Nobilitie, hir aſſiſtaris and partakaris, ſeikis be all meanis, ſorce and power thay may, to depois our ſaid Souerane of his Authoritie Royall: and for mair haiſtie performing thairof ar al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reddy conuenit in armes, for the Inuaſioun of our ſaid maiſt vndoutit Soueranes Regent, and Gouernour, Iames Erle of Murray, &amp;c. and all vtheris his partakaris and aſſiſtaris, townis, caſtellis, cieteis, and haill liegis of this Realme: qubilkis will not obey and aſſiſt thame in thair vnnaturall and vngodly procedingis. For eſchewing quhairof, ſertifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioun, mantening and defending of our ſaid vndoutit Souerane, now in his tender age, and his Regent foirſaid. The ſaidis Capitane and Proueſt for thame ſelfis, and takand the burdene vpon thame, for the vtheris aboue writtin accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thair boundin dewtie and aith of fidelitie, geuin to thair maiſt vndoutit and nariue Souerane, for mantenance of him and his authoritie Royall, ar bundin, obliſt and ſworne, be the faith and treuth in thair bodyis, lyke as be thir pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentis thay bind, obliſch and ſweiris be thair greit aithis, in all tymes cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, to tak afald, trew, and plane part togidder forthe defence of our ſaid Souerane, his Authoritie and perſoun Royall. And either of thame, with thair haill force, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and power, to fortifie, aſſiſt, and mantene vtheris with thair bodyis and gudis, and to concur and pas togidder at all tymes and to all places neidfull: not onlie for the defence of the ſaid caſtell, toun, leigis, habitantis &amp; ſubſtances yair of: but alſwa for the mantenance, ayde and defence of our ſaid Souerane his Authoritie Royall and Regent foirſaid, aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis all and ſindrie, that fall pretend to Inuaid, moleſt or perſew thame or ony of thame. And to ayde and ſupport vtheris with quhatſumeuer thing is neceſſare in thair poſſeſſiounis, or ſalbe poſſibill to thame to do, for the defence of vtheris, as neid ſall requyre. And farther, that nouther of thame fall heir, ſe, nor acknawledge the dampnage or hurt of vtheris in thair perſonis, landis or gudis, bot ſall Incontinent warne vtheris thairof, with all haiſt poſſibill: let, ſtop, and mak im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to the ſamin, at thair vtter power. And finally, ſall nouther contract, compone, tak appointment or mak aggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance by vtheris, but fall with thair haill poweris fortifie, defend and mantene vtheris in the cauſis abone writtin, but feinȝe or diſſimulatioun: contrare and aganis all that leuis or die may, that ſall happin to pretend to troubill or moleſt our ſaid Souerane in his Authoritie Royall, his ſaid Regent, aſſiſtatis and partakaris, this toun, caſtell, liegis, and haill In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantis thairof, for the cauſis foirſaidis. In witnes of the quhilk, to thir preſent letteris of Iudentouris and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſubſcriuit with our handis, our ſignet is affixt at the ſaid Burgh day ȝeir and place foriſaid, befoir thir witneſſis Schir Williame Maitland of Lethingtoun ȝounger Knicht, Maiſter Iames Makgill of Rankelour Nether, Clerk of Regiſtar, Maiſter Archebald Dowglas Perſoun of that Ilk, and Dauid Foreſt Generall with vtheris diuers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>W. Kirkcaldie.</item>
                     <item>Craigmillar Knicht</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprentit at Edinburgh be Robert Lekpreuik ANNO. DO. M.D.LXXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
